<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[An] answer to a scandalous letter lately printed and subscribed by Peter Welsh, procurator for the Sec. and Reg. popish priests of Ireland Intituled, A letter desiring a just and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland, given about the end of Octob. 1660. to the then Marquess, now Duke of Ormond, and the second time Lord Lieutenant of that Kingdom. By the right honourable the Earl of Orrery, one of the Lords Justices of the kingdom of Ireland, and L. President of the province of Munster, &amp;c. Being a full discovery of the treachery of the Irish rebels since the beginning of the rebellion there, necessary to be considered by all adventureres and other persons estated in that kingdom.</title>
            <author>Orrery, Roger Boyle, Earl of, 1621-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38538</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38538)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1838:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[An] answer to a scandalous letter lately printed and subscribed by Peter Welsh, procurator for the Sec. and Reg. popish priests of Ireland Intituled, A letter desiring a just and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland, given about the end of Octob. 1660. to the then Marquess, now Duke of Ormond, and the second time Lord Lieutenant of that Kingdom. By the right honourable the Earl of Orrery, one of the Lords Justices of the kingdom of Ireland, and L. President of the province of Munster, &amp;c. Being a full discovery of the treachery of the Irish rebels since the beginning of the rebellion there, necessary to be considered by all adventureres and other persons estated in that kingdom.</title>
                  <author>Orrery, Roger Boyle, Earl of, 1621-1679.</author>
                  <author>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688. Letter desiring a just and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Dublin by J.C. and reprinted at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue, with title page partially reset (ornaments removed and replaced with text beginning "Being a full discovery") and a copy of "A letter" added, of Wing O473.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walsh, Peter, 1618?-1688. --  Letter desiring a just and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38538:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38538:1"/>
            <p>ANSWER To a Scandalous LETTER Lately Printed and Subſcribed By PETER WELSH, Procurator for The Sec. and Reg. Popiſh Prieſts of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>INTITULED, [<hi>A Letter deſiring a juſt and merciful Regard of the Roman Catholicks of</hi> Ireland, <hi>given about the end of</hi> Octob. 1660. <hi>to the then Marqueſs, now Duke of</hi> Ormond, <hi>and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time Lord Lievtenant of that Kingdom.</hi>]</p>
            <p>By the Right Honourable The EARL of ORRERY, One of the Lords Juſtices of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and L. Preſident of the Province of <hi>Munſter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being a full diſcovery of the treachery of the Iriſh Rebels ſince the beginning of the Rebellion there, neceſſary to be conſidered by all Adventurers and other perſons eſtated in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN</hi> by <hi>J. C.</hi> and Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:38538:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38538:2"/>
            <head>A Letter deſiring a juſt and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> given about the end of <hi>October 1660</hi> to the then Marqueſs, now Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time Lord Lieutenant of that Kingdom.</head>
            <p>SInce I had the honour of ſpeaking laſt to your Excellence, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, (by occaſion of ſeveral Diſcourſes had this week with Perſons of quality) on the dayly encreaſe of the Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of my Country-men: Which is the reaſon, That inſtead of waiting on you this morning about private Concernments, (as I intended) I choſe rather out of my unalterable affection to your ſelf, to give firſt this paper, and therein my thoughts and my deſires relating to the publick, that is, to your ſelf, and to his Majeſty, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, I thought fit to tell you, That conſidering the General fear ſeiz'd already almoſt on all the Nobility, Gentry, and others here of that Nation, and reflecting on the vaſt differen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e betwixt my own beliefe and theirs, it ſeems to me, I behold (in us particularly, who have for ſo many years ſo much relyed on your word and vertue) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what fulfilled, not unlike the myſterious extinction of all the Lights to one in the Ceremony of <hi>Tenebrae</hi> in holy week. For, my Lord, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in the generality of the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland</hi> here, even (I ſay) of thoſe who have been ſo long as well your conſtant believers as your paſſionate ſticklers, a dimneſs and darkneſs ſeizing their judgments; even your faſteſt friends heretofore, looſing at preſent their faith of your future appearance for them, and hopes of their delivery by you at any time evermore: Some through ignorance of State affairs, and intrigues obſtructing as yet: others through inconſideration of thoſe wayes you take much wiſer, though ſlower, than folly and raſhneſs could chalk out: and ſome out of prejudice or an evil paſſion, which blinds them and makes them abuſe the timorouſneſs and credulity of all they can, to leſſen your eſteem and your dependencies, all they are able.</p>
            <p>My Lord, theſe are thoughts, which more and more trouble me dayly: becauſe I have dayly new occaſions to reflect on them. And therefore would no longer but give them your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Excellence, even in this method and in writing, that they might take the deeper impreſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as very much concerning you, ſince your own welfare, and the Kings and the peoples (in my judgment) very much depends on a good eſteem of ſo great a Miniſter, as your great deſerts have made you.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38538:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But withall, My Lord, I will give your excellence my moſt earneſt, and moſt humble deſires that you delay no longer than ſhall be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to clear theſe clouds of darkneſs: and clear them in this preſent conjuncture, by an effectual demonſtration of that juſtice and favour you intended the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in your Articles of 48. when they ſo freely put themſelves and their power into your hands. I am not ignorant that ſome have after tranſgreſſed in a high nature. But you know, my Lord, there are many thouſands of Proteſtants in the three Kingdomes, who have been far more hainouſly criminal, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty and againſt his Father, of bleſſed Memory, and who have contributed, or intended as little for bringing home his Majeſty, as the moſt wickedly principled of the Roman Confederates of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And we all know (my Lord) that all the Proteſtants are not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned (except a very few of the moſt immediate Regicides (but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled in all capacities with his Majeſties moſt faithful and approved ſubjects. Yet if theſe unfortunate Catholick tranſgreſſors muſt be alone, in this general <hi>Jubile</hi> of the three Nations, held unworthy to rejoyce in the Kings reſtauration; if they alone, beſides their moſt grievous and moſt unparallel'd ſufferings under tyranny theſe eight or nine years paſt, muſt anew ſuffer, and yet a more heavy judgment, under the moſt clement Prince on earth; if they alone muſt experience all the rigour of his Lawes and judicatures for their offences after the peace of 48. (which offences however criminal were not bloudy) your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence may be nevertheleſs pleaſed to conſider the Tranſplantation cannot be continued on any ſuch account, nor on any other which may ſtand either with thoſe Articles, or with the equity of the Lawes, and much leſſe with the juſtice of a Prince whom God hath reſtored to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the oppreſſed from the yoak of tyranny, <hi>to lead captivity captive, and give gifts to men.</hi> And your Excellence may be further pleaſed to conſider that the Corporations generally cannot be excluded on this account, nor on any other may ſtand with his Majeſties gracious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions in theſe Articles. Neither do I think there can be any reaſons of State may accord with the dictates of a good conſcience to exclude them. I confeſs, my Lord, the undutifulneſs of ſome, two or three peradventure deſerved puniſhment, and <hi>Limerick</hi> a ſevere one. But this, my Lord, is long ſince inflicted by the hands of God and man. The plague and famine, the ſword and gibber, even by the power of tyrants deſtroyed them, and reveng'd your quarrel; though, I am ſure, you are more divinely principled than to mind your own revenge on any. Beſides, my Lord, your Excellence knowes there have been very many faithful ſubjects in theſe towns, even in the moſt crimina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them.</p>
            <p>My Lord, you are more juſt than to involve the juſt in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked. God, himſelf, whoſe power cannot be limited by Laws, would not puniſh the juſt, not even when he was moſt incenſed by the moſt criminal Cities that ever ſtood on earth. He aſſured the prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that could he find one juſt man in all <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (when moſt ſinful and reprobate, and by his revenging juſtice deſign'd for a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38538:3"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eneral deſolation) he would ſingle out that man from the wicked and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave him (for ſo our tranſlation reads) nay, for his ſake be merciful to the whole City (if your Tranſlation be right.) When the crying ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> forc'd open the flood-gates of heaven to power down thoſe prodigious flames of fire and brimſtone, we read in <hi>Geneſis</hi> yet would not the juſtice of God permit execution, before he had put in a place of ſafety one juſt man that was found in <hi>Sodom.</hi> And, which is yet more obſervable, was further pleaſed to aſſure <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he was ſo far from intending to involve the juſt in the deſtruction of the wicked, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theſe great places deſign'd for ſo great vengeance, he could find but even ten juſt men, he would for their ſake pardon all the reſt, that is, not <hi>Sodom</hi> alone, but the five Cities, and the whole Pentapolitane region annexed. My Lord, our gracious King hath in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitation of this mercy of God, pardon'd for ſome juſt mens ſake all the Proteſtant Cities of his Dominions. And will he not pardon the miſerable remainders of one poor Catholick Town? or two? or three at moſt? if perhaps there be ſo many that have any way offended. I am ſure, what ever their offence hath been, it hath been theſe many years paſt ſufficiently puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d: and hath been, even of the moſt criminal, incomparably leſs than what may be charged on moſt of all his Majeſties Proteſtant Cities. And I am ſure there have been in the very worſt of them, and in the moſt diſobedient more than fifty (the greateſt number <hi>Abraham</hi> propoſed for mercy to <hi>Sodom</hi>) juſt men (I ſay) to his Majeſty, and your Excellence; then which you take no further cognizance of juſtice in this particular. And what beſides may render them unfit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the general mercy, if not perhaps their Religion? Which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, being ſo Chrſtian, and allowed by Articles, can be no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet if notwithſtanding all this, the few and miſerable Survivours and Heirs of the dead in the general deſolation, muſt ſuffer again, and under his royal juſtice: I beſeech you (my Lord) Let not the Tables of <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> let not their general proſcriptions or confiſcations be renewed on this occaſion, or affixed in the Courts and Judicatures of the Brittiſh Monarchy. Let not theſe bright dayes of univerſal joy, be rendred to the Iriſh Catholicks alone dark, ſad, and diſmal. Nor let theſe dayes be infamouſly memorable to poſterity for a diſtinction ſo unequal. Even the greateſt and worſt of Delinquents, amongſt the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> even of thoſe very Corporations or Cities, that have been moſt refractory, were ſo far from being Regicides, or any way inclined unto them, (and only ſuch, and but very few of ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe only ſome of the moſt immediate actors, have been hitherto thought fit to be excluded a ſhare in this joy) that they have fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them even to deſpair: and fought againſt them when <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> wholly deſerted the Royal cauſe: and fought againſt them as well in defence of his Majeſties rights as under the title of his Subjects; till at laſt by long ſeiges, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes overpowred, and through Gods unſearchable. Judgments, and their deſertion by friends abroad, and home diviſions they loſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Country.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, my Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be it from my thoughts to deſire the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of any lawfull and honeſt courſe may be juſtly taken to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38538:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> the peace of that Country from rational dangers: if any ſuch can be in our dayes from the Catholick Natives. What I humbly beg is, That if theſe Catholicks muſt be alwayes ſo unfortunate as to be thought unworthy His Majeſties Graces and Favours to Proteſtants that fought againſt him, when they fought for him, or of ſuch as he vouchſafes; even Presbyters, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Fift-monarchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Independents (the greateſt Enemies to regal power in ſome Tenets, wherein the Roman Catholicks are the ſureſt friends) his Majeſty may be at leaſt graciouſly pleaſed to let them have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Conceſſions articled with them. And what I beg, my Lord, is that his Majeſty not ſo much regard the power of our Adverſaries as the Juſtice of our cauſe. My Lord, their power is no greater at this time, than His Majeſty is pleaſed to continue or make it. There is a huge difference betwixt their influence on the meaner Officers and common Souldiers now, and that it was in the time of the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or in the dayes of Tyranny and Anarchy. In a word it will ſignifie a meer nothing, if once uncommiſſioned by His Majeſty, and the common Souldiers payed.</p>
            <p>However, my Lord, their power cannot be ſo dangerous, as their unjuſt demands of byaſſed intereſt and pretended zeal, if complyed withall by His Majeſty, and by a breach ſo notorious and ſo great of our Articles. For, beſides that ſuch proceedings would, in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, eſtrange the hearts of the Iriſh Catholicks from his Majeſty, and by a conſequence of reaſon (how ſtrange ſoever this may appear at firſt ſight) kindle and raiſe in all judicious Proteſtants who have ever fought in any of his Dominions, either againſt himſelf, or againſt his Father, even in the very Demanders (how much ſoever blinded at preſent by proper intereſt) perpetual Jealouſies, and diſtruſts of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own ſafety, notwithſtanding any Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> or Acts of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> paſs'd in this preſent Parliament: they would, (which is moſt of all to be feared as the worſt of evils, and may Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence divert it in obſtructing the cauſe) turn the heart of God from our good Prince; and bring his Judgments on him. My Lord, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or ſcarce ever did publick breach of publick faith eſcape very publick and very dreadfull Judgments, even in this World, I mean. Hiſtories profane and ſacred are full of ſad examples of both kinds. And for the peoples breach, our Iriſh Nation theſe fourteen years paſt ſo wonderfully ſcourged beyond almoſt all example, for their breach of their firſt Articles, thoſe of fourty ſix, with you (my Lord) will be recorded in after ages as one of the ſaddeſt. But for a Princes tranſgreſſion of this nature, and Judgments following, even ſuch as are infallibly known to have been for this only cauſe inflicted, and by God's own immediate execution for the greateſt part, and the reſt by his good will and pleaſure, that of the 21. of the 2. of <hi>Samuel</hi> is pertinent and formidable. The very firſt of faithfull Kings, elected by Gods immediate ordinance, anointed by God's immediate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, appointed by him Ruler of his peculiar people, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion on Earth of his Church againſt Infidels; even this beloved of
<pb facs="tcp:38538:4"/> God for a time, this dear darling of Heaven for ſome years, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attempted againſt Articles, on the poor <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and their four Cities, but thoſe moſt fearfull and exemplar Judgments, recorded by <hi>Samuel,</hi> were decreed againſt him, and, for this very fact alone, againſt his poſterity, and againſt the whole Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Neither could all the miſeries of his own life after, nor the ignominy of his own death, and of the beſt of his children, which followed very ſoon, nor the Army of God periſhing with him by the ſwords of Idolaters, expiate this publick breach of publick Articles. Not although they were his own Subjects with whom he broke, and not Subjects only, but ſlaves born, and by covenant; nor ſlaves alone, but Amorites, whoſe Towns and Lands, and fortunes had been the free gift of God to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in his promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> 700. years before, and long after appropriated the ſecond time unto them by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by his particular command for extirpation of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inhabitants, and of the Amorites by name, and for never entring any League or Peace or Covenant with them. Not although theſe <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> when they articled by their Predeceſſors, were Infidels, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of one true God, and their Articles made with true believers, and believers infallibly ſuch, and not with <hi>Saul,</hi> but with <hi>Joſue,</hi> 300. years before the Raign of <hi>Saul,</hi> and never by him ratified. Nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, what is more obſervable, theſe Articles were obtained of <hi>Joſhua</hi> through his ignorance of the people that treated with him, and by their lies and circumvention of him. Nor finally, although theſe Articles were aſſented unto by <hi>Joſhua</hi> only, and his twelve chief Captains; the whole multitude (concern'd in this buſineſs) not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting otherwiſe; as appeared within three dayes after the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by their general murmur againſt the Prince. My Lord, note of all theſe extenuating circumſtances, nor altogether, not even back't with zeal for the people of God (the ſcripture noting particularly that <hi>Saul ſought to ſlay the Gibeonites in his zeal to the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah) no excuſe, no pretence whatſoever could obtain ſo much mercy of the great Juſticier of Heaven, as to inflict the puniſhment of this article-breaking on the perſon of <hi>Saul</hi> alone; not even together with his beloved <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s, or on his Legions, and People in his own dayes only. The vengeance of God muſt purſue his Poſterity and Kingdom, long after his death, and for this cauſe alone. A mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Famine of three years continuance muſt conſume the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even in the reign of his Succeſſor; and for this very ſin only, as God himſelf revealed to holy <hi>David.</hi> Nor would the Famine ceaſe, till by <hi>David's</hi> commandment ſeven of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Children and Nephews were delivered to the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> and by the hands of theſe very men, whoſe Articles he broke, crucified alive upon a Mountain, to expiate this publick and horrid ſin, even in the face of the ſun. May Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the Kings Righteouſneſs, and your ſage Counſel (my Lord) obſtruct all occaſions of reflecting on this, (and ſo many other examples of God's revenge of Article-breaking) any further than that the beſt of Kings may ſee the worſts of evils attending the Counſels of
<pb facs="tcp:38538:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> our Adverſaries: and that their power, whatever it be, cannot be ſo dangerous as their demands againſt our Articles.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I conclude here, but with my hearty wiſhes, That in the Houſe, and at the Councels of our great King, your Excellence may both appear and approve your ſelf hereafter what you are in part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, another <hi>Joſeph.</hi> That by the beſt of Advices you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the beſt of Princes, and all his people of ſo many different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Brittiſh monarchy. May it be ſo, my Lord! And may the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland</hi> in particular owe you a great Deliverance! as I cannot but confidently expect from you in due time; for my light in the triangle cannot be extinguiſhed. But (my Lord) may not innocent beloved <hi>Benjamin</hi> alone, nor friendly <hi>Reuben</hi> only, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> and their Complices againſt you heretofore, have cauſe to bleſs God for you hereafter. May they all find in effect, that you have the bowels of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to forgive and compaſſionate them, and his power to deliver them, and his faith to believe, That God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their evil againſt you, even in forcing you twice away from them, of purpoſe to preſerve you for their good; and that you might return, even this ſecond time, their great Deliverer. Propitious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and your own good <hi>Genius,</hi> my Lord, ſecond my wiſhes! And may your faithfull believer ſee with his own eyes the full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! that he may employ all his dayes after, and all his Labours in conſecrating to poſterity your Name, with this <hi>Elogium</hi> of <hi>Joſeph, the Saviour of his Brethren, and of his Country, and of all the People.</hi> And theſe are the hearty wiſhes of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(<hi>My Lord</hi>)</salute>
               <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble, moſt obſequious, and moſt devoted Servant, P. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38538:5"/>
            <head>The Anſwer. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving lately ſeen a Printed Paper, the Title whereof is, [<hi>A Letter deſiring a just and merciful regard of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland, given about the end of October, 1660. to the then Marqueſs, now Duke of</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, <hi>and the ſecond time L. Lievtenant of that Kingdom:</hi>] Subſcribed by <hi>P. W.</hi> And finding it in effect, whatever the words of it are, <hi>extreemly undutiful to his ſacred Majeſty, very diſreſpectful to the Duke of</hi> Ormond <hi>L. Lievtenant of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and moſt ſcandalous not only to the Protestants of</hi> Ireland, <hi>but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to thoſe of the ſame Religion in his ſacred Majeſties other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes:</hi> I have eſteemed my ſelf obliged, <hi>as a faithfull ſubject to the King, as an humble ſervant to the L. Lievtenant, and as a ſon of the Proteſtant Church,</hi> whoſe Members are as highly as falſely aſperſt by it, to expoſe in print an Anſwer to that Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which before I enter upon, I will only ſay, <hi>P. W.</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing not a little to be his Graces ſervant, if he meant not this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as a reſpect to his Grace, why was it <hi>written?</hi> if he did, why was it <hi>printed?</hi> But <hi>P. W.</hi> deſpairing to receive from His Grace the effects of his <hi>unjuſt deſires</hi> for his Country-men, choſe this way to acquaint them, 'twas not for want of <hi>his ſollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> He would let them ſee, ſince he could not make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to <hi>My L. Lievtenant,</hi> that they were ſo to <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since I ſhall often have occaſion to name IRISH PAPISTS.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38538:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> I have thought fit here, once for all, to declare, That I mean not thereby in all, or any part of my anſwer any of thoſe <hi>Worthy</hi> perſons of that Nation and Religion who have <hi>ſtill faithfully ſerved the King,</hi> whoſe merit I highly reſpect, and the more, becauſe it has been preſerved from <hi>infection</hi> even in a very <hi>Peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe;</hi> nor any of thoſe, who having been truly ſorrowful for having rebell'd in the conſtancy of their ſubſequent ſervices to his Majeſty, have waſht themſelves clean; For I take a perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in any change from <hi>bad to good;</hi> and I heartly wiſh, that every one of them had not ſo much endangered their being pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted again, as interceding and pleading for their guilty Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men does amount unto. Having thus made this neceſſary digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I ſhall now proceed.</p>
            <p>The parts ſeparate of this Letter are three. Firſt, a Preface. Secondly, a Petition. Thirdly, a Concluſion or concluding Wiſh. <hi>P. W.</hi> prefaceth, Firſt, the <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> of thoſe whom he calls the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Secondly, <hi>His own affection to, and confidence in his Grace the Duke of</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> are no leſs than muſt in reaſon be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in the <hi>Generality of the Iriſh Papists;</hi> For though the goodneſs and indulgence of the beſt of Kings may make their condition ſafe: yet the conſcience of their own guilt will never ſuffer them to be ſecure. Pretended Fears and Jealouſies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were the Forerunners, if not Cauſers of <hi>Troubles past;</hi> I hope <hi>P. W.</hi> intends them not as ſuch, <hi>for Troubles to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fear is founded on, at leaſt attended with Hatred; and if one of the beſt of His Majeſties Servants, one of the chiefeſt of his Miniſters, be thus, 1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally, 2. Intenſly fear'd,</hi> and therefore 3. <hi>hated,</hi> 4. as <hi>P. W.</hi> ſayes, by his own Country-men: (but let all that <hi>P. W.</hi> prints, ſtand or fall, as this laſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular is true or falſe; for his Grace is neither his Country-man by birth, Religion, or any other Relation to which that Name is appliable;) yea 5. by his own Fiduciares (as is expreſſed in the printed Letter.) If, I ſay, all this be not true, why does <hi>P. W.</hi> ſay it? if it be true, what can others expect? For if the flame be ſo in the green Tree, what will it be in the dry?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38538:6"/>
            <p>The Iriſh Papiſts in their former and later Apologies for the horrideſt of Rebellions, have not to this very day (within any of his Majeſties Dominions) even pretended publickly any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe for their Rapines, Murthers, Maſſacres and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but what reſolves it ſelf into Fears and Jealouſies. And if their paſſions be the ſame, it is to be fear'd their Wills are not alter'd. And if their Wills be the ſame, nothing under God, can prevent the effects, but want of ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpecially conſidering that 1. in 1641. no ſuch antecedent <hi>animoſities</hi> or <hi>hatreds</hi> had prepared matters for <hi>Fears and Jealouſies,</hi> as by the worſt of Rebellions is now become even <hi>nationally</hi> violent, (but by the way, it ſeems to me ſomewhat hard, that thoſe which give the riſe for the Cauſe, ſhould firſt cry out in the Effects.) 2. In 1641. theſe <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> (if really in any) were but in a <hi>Few;</hi> but now <hi>P. W.</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>That they have ſeized upon almost all the Nobility, Gentry and others, yea the Generality of the Catholicks of</hi> Ireland, <hi>even the conſtant Believers of, paſſionate Sticklers for, and fasteſt Friends to his Grace the Duke of</hi> Ormond; and this ſo intenſly, that it produceth <hi>the loſs both of Faith and Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it may well be obſerved what temper they are of, whom P. W. pleads for; Jealouſies, Fears and want of faith are ſo inſeparable from them, that thoſe in 1641. were only ſaid to be derived from his Majeſties Enemies, but now (all ſuch by the mercy of God being blown away) they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <hi>his Majeſties chief Miniſter of State of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> and who is made ſuch, as P. W. ſaith, and as I moſt heartily acknowledge, by his own great deſerts. What is it can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Fears and Jealouſies of P. W's. Country-men, when His Majeſties free Election of a chief Governor, and ſuch a one as the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> is, cannot do it? This acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of P. W's. fully proves, that the Iriſh Papiſts Fears and Jealouſies of the chief Governors of this Kingdom in 1641. were only taken up by thoſe, and not cauſe given for them by theſe. The plain Engliſh is this, though his Majeſtly ſhould from time to time nominate for Lord Lieutenant of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the wiſeſt and the faithfulleſt of his Subjects; yet becauſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38538:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> the King commiſſionates them, or becauſe they are ſuch, or both, many (I wiſh I could not ſay moſt) of the Iriſh Papiſts will be jealous and fearfull of them.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>P. W</hi>'s. affection to, and confidence in his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> expreſt by ſeveral inſtances <hi>of free and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acceſs to him, of his and others relyance on his word, of his daily care and trouble to ſupport his eſteem, and of blaming di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrusters as guilty of ignorance of State affairs, and the Intrigues obſtructing,</hi> as yet; <hi>or of inconſideration of thoſe wiſer ways, though ſlower, than folly or raſhneſs could chalk out, or of prejudice and evil Paſſion.</hi> I will onely ſay, That though <hi>P. W.</hi> would make us believe, as if ſome word in ſecret had paſt by his Grace to the Iriſh Papiſts, which they dare thus mention to himſelf, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the world; at leaſt that he who is a profeſt Enemy to the Engliſh intereſt, and Proteſtant Religion, is his Graces intimate and familiar Confident; and by ſuch as viſible, as falſe arts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to infect the Proteſtants with the diſeaſe of him, and his Country-men; <hi>Jealouſies and fears of the L. Lieutenant.</hi> Yet I dare as truly, as confidently averr, though <hi>P. W</hi>'s. Oratory were as great as his malice, his inſinuations could not ſhake, much leſs overthrow that irremovable confidence his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> have built with great reaſon and experience upon his Grace, even on the double Accompts, of his <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes.</hi> To attempt to betray with a Kiſs, is neither a new Art or a new Sin, but he that would deſtroy by undermining, would do it by open force, if his Power proportioned his Will.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>P. W.</hi>'s affection to his Grace, he ſayes no more for that in particular, than he ſayes in general for his Country-mens having a right to the Peace made in 1648. Therefore I believe his Grace will take his meaſure of <hi>the former, by his knowledge of the later.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Preface, <hi>P. W.</hi> petitions, <hi>That his Grace would no longer delay, than ſhall be neceſſary, yea that be would in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conjuncture, effectually demonſtrate that juſtice and favour h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intended to the Catholicks of</hi> Ireland, <hi>in the Articles of Peace made in</hi> 1648.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>P. W.</hi> in the firſt clauſe, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons onely that his Grace
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38538:7"/> 
               <hi>would no longer delay than ſhall be neceſſary;</hi> yet as if ſtruck with the Fears and Jealouſies of his Countrey-men, and not daring to ſubmit the determination of that period of neceſſity to his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces judgement, he petitions limitedly, if not poſitively, in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter clauſe, for <hi>the preſent conjuncture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the ſubject matter of that Juſtice and Favour petitioned for, may be meaſur'd (as is expreſt) by his Graces intendment, I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confident the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould his Majeſty think fit) will freely ſubmit their All, to that Deciſion; without either ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticling with him firſt; or breaking Articles after the guilt of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P. W.</hi> inforceth his Petition by Arguments pretending to</p>
            <list>
               <head>Juſtice</head>
               <item>Diſtributive
<list>
                     <item>In the common caſe conſider'd
<list>
                           <item>Abſolutely.</item>
                           <item>Comparatively</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Communitive
<list>
                     <item>In ſome ſpecial caſes of the
<list>
                           <item>Tranſplantation. Corporation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In reſpect of the <hi>common Caſe</hi> conſidered <hi>abſolutely,</hi> P. W. argues, That the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts in 1648. FREELY put themſelves and their power into his Graces hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Freely</hi> in this inſtance, if it ſignifies ought meritoriouſly, it ſignifies the ſame as <hi>gratis;</hi> when as it was made, 1. upon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; 2. even upon <hi>ſuch</hi> Articles, as forced from his Majeſty all the <hi>Regalia,</hi> both <hi>Eccleſiastical</hi> and <hi>Temporal;</hi> 3. when as at ſuch a <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and in ſuch a <hi>tempest</hi> every good Subject ſhould <hi>freely</hi> have caſt his Goods over-board, to prevent the <hi>common Wrack,</hi> even then the Iriſh Papiſts would not contribute to prevent one Leak, but at a <hi>Rate</hi> unproportionate, and as the Tempeſt or Leaks <hi>increaſed,</hi> ſo <hi>increaſed</hi> their <hi>Rates.</hi> But to ſhow how <hi>freely</hi> the Iriſh put themſelves and their power into his Majeſties hands, I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> need but rehearſe his ſacred Majeſties own words, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of his Majeſties Gracious Declaration of the 30. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1660. page 3. <hi>viz. We well remember the Ceſſation of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38538:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Peace, which Our Royal Father of bleſſed Memory had been</hi> FORCED, <hi>during the late Troubles, to make with his Iriſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that Our Kingdom, and by which he was</hi> COMPELLED <hi>to give them a full pardon for what they had before done amiſs, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on their return to their duty, and their promiſe of giving his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty a vigorous aſſiſtance.</hi> In the ſame page of the ſame Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſoon after follow theſe words, <hi>viz. We could not forget the Peace which Our ſelves was afterwards</hi> NECESSITATED <hi>to make with our ſaid Subjects, in the time when they who wickedly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped the Authority, had erected that odious Court for the taking away the life of Our dear Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That which his Majeſty calls <hi>Forced, Compelled,</hi> and <hi>Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated,</hi> P. W. <hi>Freely putting themſelves into his Graces hands;</hi> ſo that that untrue ſuggeſtion of his needs no other refutation as to the time paſt, and as to the time to come, I wiſh I had not cauſe to doubt, if ever they put themſelves into his Graces hand, that which they will call Freely, will be an effect of Compulſion, Force and Neceſſity. Whatever the Submiſſion was in 1648. and how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Free ſoever pretended; yet the expreſs letter of thoſe Articles, (Article 18.) precludes all Offences which ſhall be committed or done after their Date; and after that, the Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts inſtead of <hi>freely putting themſelves and their powers into the L. Lieutenants hands,</hi> ſignally declared their Contempt of him, Diſobedience to him, and Oppoſition againſt him. For proofs whereof, among many, I ſhall ſet down one undenyable inſtance of each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For their <hi>Contempts:</hi> In April 1650. by a Meſſage they deſired the L. Lievtenant to <hi>Leave</hi> the Kingdome, and commit the Government to <hi>one of their own election,</hi> in whom they could <hi>confide.</hi> That which <hi>Now</hi> P. W. varniſheth with a modeſter phraſe of <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> was then contempt and diffidence. At the ſame time that they own'd the L. Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants Authority, they deſire him to reſign it, without his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties conſent, nay ſo much as his knowledge; yet this is but conſonant to the whole Series of their practiſes, never to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the <hi>Kings Right,</hi> but to <hi>affront it, or to get their ends by it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38538:8"/>2. For their <hi>Diſobedience</hi> when the L. Lievtenant refuſed upon weighty reaſons of Piety, Duty, and State, to conform to this Meſſage, and leave the Kingdom; in Auguſt following they by their publick Declaration profeſſed their Diſſobedience in theſe very words: <hi>We do hereby manifest to the people, that they are no longer oblig'd to obey the Orders or Commands of the Marqueſs of</hi> Ormond. Words which ſo clearly evidence their Rebellion, and the vaſtneſſe of it, that they need no Comment, nor ought but the Text it ſelf to prove both thoſe Truths. Nor is there need of any other proof to evince their intire breach of thoſe Articles which they now ſo fiercly plead for the benefit of. They are ſo far from giving proofs of their duty to the King, and of their gratitude for his Mercy extended in thoſe Articles; that leaſt any ſhould ſuſpect them guilty of <hi>thoſe,</hi> they declare their power <hi>paramount to his Majesties Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They proceed from <hi>bad</hi> to <hi>worſe,</hi> from <hi>worſe</hi> to <hi>worst;</hi> from <hi>Contempt</hi> to <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> from <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Oppoſition.</hi> And accordingly the very next moneth they cauſe their Clergy to excommunicate <hi>not onely the L. Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but all that ſhould feed, or adhere to him.</hi> That which Chriſt commands us to do to our enemies; (<hi>if thy enemy hunger, feed him;</hi>) and that which even common Charity makes us do to the very beggars at our gates, they not only refuſe to do to him they ſo recently acknowledged to have his Majeſties Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nay who had the honour to repreſent his perſon: but alſo they prohibit all others to do it, and upon no leſſe penalty than Excommunication; and that nothing may be wanting to ſublimate their wickedneſſe to the higheſt, Religion is made the inſtrument of their iniquity.</p>
            <p>The Notoriety whereof, and of many other acts diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally oppoſite to that <hi>free</hi> ſubmiſſion immediately pretended, is ſo undeniable, that P. W's. own Conſcience <hi>ſqueezeth</hi> out this confeſſion, <hi>I am not ignorant that ſome have after tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a high nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But firſt, the aformentioned Declaration runs in the name of the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland;</hi> now <hi>ſome,</hi> was then <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, All the premiſed inſtances of <hi>Contempt, Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38538:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>Oppoſition</hi> were not the Acts of private, but of <hi>publick</hi> perſons, even of thoſe publick perſons <hi>into whoſe hands the Iriſh Papists may truly be ſaid to have gratis put themſelves and their power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The general ſilence and <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> of the body of the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> to the premiſed inſtances, concluſively argues, <hi>a general conſent</hi> thereunto, at leaſt <hi>ſubſequent,</hi> if not <hi>antecedent;</hi> for either they were <hi>generally conſenting,</hi> or <hi>diſſenting;</hi> if <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> why did not that Generality puniſh the Tranſgreſſors, or even oppoſe and deny the Tranſgreſſion? if <hi>generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> that extenuating patricle <hi>ſome,</hi> declares more affection in P. W. to thoſe <hi>Conſenters,</hi> than either to His Majeſty or his Viceroy.</p>
            <p>The next argument reſpecting the <hi>General Caſe,</hi> is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by way of <hi>Compariſon,</hi> and that as frequent as untrue, charging, (1.) <hi>Proteſtants, (2.) Many Proteſtants, (3.) Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand Proteſtants, (4.) In the three Kingdoms; 1. To have been more hainouſly criminal; 2. To have contributed, or intended as little for the bringing home of his Majeſty, as the moſt wickedly principled of the Roman Catholicks of</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>If ever any, this Compariſon is odious, between <hi>many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proteſtants</hi> in the three Kingdoms, and not barely the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> but the moſt wickedly principled of them: ſo that if P. W. may hold the ſcale, the Crimes of thoſe Proteſtants ſhall weigh more, and their Services for His Majeſty, at leaſt their intendments, leſs.</p>
            <p>But let P. W. prove any one of thoſe many Thouſands thus wickedly principled to be a Proteſtant, and he will with the ſame labour diſprove his charge. Let him prove his charge in any one particular, and he will with the ſame labour diſprove his inſtance to be a Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>I believe moſt in the three Kingdoms have been firſt or laſt hainouſly criminal, ſo that every mouth muſt be ſtopped. But certainly their guilt gradually differs, and the moſt wickedly principled of the Roman Catholicks of <hi>Ireland</hi> deſerve not the loweſt degrees in it. Yet poſſibly ſome others in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms may run parallel with them; but I aſſume, ſuch are more
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38538:9"/> cloſely allied both in principle and practiſe, to the Iriſh Papiſt, than Engliſh Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe all be involved in one Common guilt, <hi>is the eye of P. W. evil, becauſe his Majesties is good?</hi> or, is there any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to extend the ſame Grace to all; or to render a Reaſon, where only Grace makes the difference? I preſume P. W. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects a greater degree of favour than many others of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, and therefore his Fears and Jealouſies are leſs; his affection and confidence more; and may not his Majeſties Grace make a general as well as perſonal difference?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As God who is glorious in all perfections, doth magnifie his Mercy above all his works: ſo his Majeſty who abounds in all Royal virtues, doth above all abound in Grace and Goodneſs, and from that Grace and Goodneſs, without the leſt pretenſion of merit (the Popiſh tenent) or Articling, (the Iriſh practiſe) the Engliſh Proteſtants confeſs to derive their All. Yet they humbly conceive, there are rational in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements for His Majeſty in the degrees of his Grace, to diſcriminate between the Iriſh Papiſts and the Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In all <hi>Societies</hi> the publick acts of <hi>FREE Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> virtually and interpretatively include all, who declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively <hi>oppoſe</hi> not. But the <hi>Engliſh Repreſentative,</hi> though under a Force, would never conſent to caſt off his Majeſties Authority, and as ſoon as freed from Force, brought home his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; the Iriſh when at moſt freedom, and after a ſubmiſſion pretended, diſtruſted, diſobeyed, oppoſed his Majeſties Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; yea baniſh'd and excommunicated (him <hi>in effigie</hi> in) his Viceroy; and his, namely, all that ſhould <hi>feed</hi> him or <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here</hi> to him; nor did they ever as a <hi>publick Repreſentative,</hi> either witneſſe their repentance, or contribute to his Majeſties Reſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Engliſh Proteſtants, as became Subjects, ſubmitted to his Majeſty freely and abſolutely; but the Iriſh Papiſts, as became Enemies, not only articled with his Majeſty, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him in the day of their <hi>height</hi> and his <hi>neceſſity,</hi> to ſuch Articles, as they knew nothing but neceſſity could compell him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38538:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to. The Engliſh Proteſtants may therefore claim his Majeſties Grace, which is as great as their guilt; the Iriſh Papiſts can only claim what is due by Articles, the foundation whereof being diſſolv'd on their parts, they can juſtly claim nothing by them, though his Majeſtiss mercy has given them much.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The forfeited Eſtates of the Engliſh Proteſtants were fully at his Majeſties diſpoſe, and might be freely remitted; but the forfeited eſtates of the Iriſh Papiſts were ſold by his late Majeſty of bleſſed memory, and that ſale for the ſatisfaction of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers, countenanced and declared in Parliament, and therefore the forfeited Eſtate of the Iriſh Papiſts could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted without ſatisfaction to the Innocent Purchaſers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His Majeſty may rationally expect more future Obedience and Loyalty from Engliſh Proteſtants, than Iriſh Papiſts. For (1) the Engliſh Proteſtants are the Conquerours, the Iriſh Papiſts the Conquered, and ancient as well as modern experience has made it appear, the <hi>Conquered</hi> never did (ſome think morally never will) love the <hi>Conqueror;</hi> and though his Majeſty ſhould give the Iriſh Papiſts not the half only, but the whole of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: yet they will never probably forgive the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants for conquering them, nor conſequently heartily love that Royal authority which firſt commiſſionated the Proteſtants to do it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Untill theſe laſt unhappy and unnatural troubles, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Proteſtants in Ireland were never charg'd as guilty of any Rebellion; but the Iriſh Papiſts in all opportunities never other than rebellious. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was the mirror of her age, yet during all her Reign the Rebellions of the Iriſh Papiſts in Ireland were very frequent. King <hi>James</hi> was another <hi>Solomon,</hi> a Prince of peace, yet was his peace interrupted by the Rebellion of Iriſh Papiſts, and by that only. King <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt was a greater than that <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the wiſeſt of men thought the Iriſh Papiſts faſten'd in 1641 to his Majeſty by the beſt of Goverments; and to the Engliſh Proteſtants, by the ſtricteſt Tyes of Intereſs, friendſhip, marriage and (which is more in their eſteem) <hi>Goſſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Fostering;</hi> to the publick peace, by their as flouriſhing, ſo free condition; and to all, by thoſe Royal Graces which his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38538:10"/> ſacred Majeſty at that time indulg'd their Commiſſioners, ſuch as themſelves could deſire; 'twas then but ask and have: yet all this Honey turn'd into Gall; for at that very time in which the King was exerciſing ſuch high acts of Grace to them, the Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts plotted, and ſoon after perpetrated the worſt of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the worſt <hi>extenſivè,</hi> exulcerating generally; and <hi>intenſivè,</hi> breaking forth with more perfidy, barbariſm and cruelty than can be parallel'd in any Hiſtory.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Principles of Religion ingage Engliſh Proteſtants to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the King as Supreme; but Principles of Religion ingage Iriſh Papiſts to advance as Supreme a Foreign Prince, and limits all their obedience, with a <hi>Saving to the pretended Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick See.</hi> Certainly his Majeſty may expect more future obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from Proteſtants, whoſe Conſciences ingage them to Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; than from Iriſh Papiſts, whoſe Conſciences are ingaged to the Pope. Can his Majeſty truſt them, if they be not faithfull to their Conſcience-ingagement? and if they be, can he truſt them when their Conſciences ingage them to his Enemy?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The next ſort of Arguments reſpect ſome ſpecial Caſes, as (1) of the Tranſplantation, (2) of the Corporation.</head>
               <p>Concerning the Tranſplantation, P. W. peremptorily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>That it cannot be continued on account of their Crimes ſince 1648. nor stand with the Articles, or with the equity of the Laws, much leſs with the Juſtice of the Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. This Concluſion without any proof, with the ſame facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as it is ſaid, may be gainſaid.</p>
               <p>2. The Foundation of thoſe Articles, and conſequently the Articles themſelves are thrown down by the Iriſh Papiſts; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it matters not as to his Majeſty, what can or cannot ſtand with them.</p>
               <p>3. Many other Countreys and Ages have formerly on leſſe grounds uſed Tranſplantation, and been juſtified therein as juſt and equal, by Lawyers and Caſuiſts.</p>
               <p>4. Obſerve his Sacred Majeſties Royal and Fatherly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38538:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Indulgence even to thoſe Iriſh Papiſts, who being Innocent, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out Decrees, and obtained poſſeſſion of Lands in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Connaught</hi> and County of <hi>Clare.</hi> Firſt, Poſitively; for though they had bound themſelves up therein by their own Act, in which though his Majeſty ſaith in the 14. page of his Gracious Declaration of the 30. of <hi>November 1660. We might without any injuſtice deny to relieve them;</hi> yet his Clemency is ſo great, That in the ſame 14. page of his ſaid Declaration, he breaks thoſe Fetters which they had bound themſelves in, and orders them to be reſtored unto their former eſtates.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Comparatively; his Majeſty uſes thoſe innocent Iriſh Papiſts with more tenderneſs than even thoſe which He ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors with the high Title of his <hi>Friends in England and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as appears in the 18. and 19. pages of the ſaid Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>For though ſuch are not to expect that his Majesty ſhould pay back to them the Moneys they were compelled in the evil times to disburſe for their Compoſitions, the payment whereof they would have avoiden, had it been in their power,</hi> as much as the Iriſh Papiſts would have avoided their Tranſplantation: yet his Majeſties Friends are not relieved from their own Act, when the innocent Iriſh Papiſts are relieved from theirs.</p>
               <p>5. Obſerve the inſolency of P. W. for though his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in Council, by his ſaid Declaration publiſhed to the world in print, declared that ſome other tranſplanted Iriſh are to ſtand bound by their own Act, and not to be relieved againſt it; yet P. W. is ſo far from acknowledging and magnifying his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Mercy in uſing the innocent Iriſh Papiſts with more favour, than even thoſe happy perſons whom his Majeſty honours with the high Title of being his Friends, that P. W. peremptorily ſayes, <hi>viz. The Tranſplantation cannot be continued on account of their crimes ſince 1648. nor can it ſtand with the Articles, or with the equity of the Lawes, much leſſe with the Justice of the Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. That the Juſtice of his Sacred Majeſty in Council may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be ſuch, in not breaking ſo much of the Tranſplantation, as is confirmed by the ſaid Declaration, I deſire theſe following particulars may be throughly conſidered:</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38538:11"/>
               <p>(1) If ſuch tranſplanted Iriſh Papiſts into <hi>Connaught</hi> and <hi>Clare</hi> ſhould plead that the Force of the late horrid Uſurpers conſtrained them to go thither in perſon; I anſwer, yet no Force lay upon them to ſue out Decrees, and obtain poſſeſſions of Lands there in lieu of their former ſorfeited Eſtates in the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. And it is onely in point of Land that the ſaid Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation is continued: ſo that their doing of what they could not avoid, is not made concluſive to them, but only their doing of that which they could avoid, and yet ſollicited and brought to effect, is made binding to ſome of them. To which I ſhall adde, that thoſe to whom it is made obliging, are only ſuch as having no title to innocency, (for all Innocents are freed from Tranſplantation) have no title to any of their former Eſtates. And therefore this confirming of them in the compenſation of that, to which they had no right, ſhould invite them to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Majeſties Mercy, which yet P. W. in their behalf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims againſt as injuſtice.</p>
               <p>(2) Though all theſe guilty Tranſplanted Iriſh have forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their right to the Articles extorted from his Majeſty in 1648. and though by thoſe Articles (had they been as punctually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by them, as they have been generally and often violated by themſelves yet) his Majeſty was not obliged to hinder them from making an unequal bargain or exchange for thoſe their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Lands, which by his mercy they were reſtored unto, nor to confirm to them thoſe Lands which they ſued for in ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their former Eſtates; yet his ſacred Majeſty confirms to them, in confirming their Tranſplantation, thoſe Lands which they themſelves had obtained from the Uſurpers, as a compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Lands they left, and to which they had not the leaſt ſhadow of a Title, becauſe they had broken, yea often, if not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, the ſaid Articles of peace vouchſaved to, and extorted by them, in the year 1648.</p>
               <p>(3) The perſons themſelves who are tranſplanted have by their publick Agents, made the continuance and ſettlement of the Tranſplantation the ſubject matter of ſeveral Petitions and Addreſſes to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP:</hi> therefore as for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem to decry it now, argues in them a fuller readineſſe to obey Force, than
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38538:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Right: ſo the continuance of it being in effect but a granting of their own deſires and petitions, they can juſtly blame none but Themſelves. To prove the truth of this, I ſhall ſet down the Titles and chief Heads of two petitions preſented to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP.</hi> The one is in print, and thus addreſſed: <hi>To the Supreme Authority, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c. The humble Petition of Sir</hi> Robert Talbot <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and</hi> Garrot Moor <hi>Eſq; on the behalf of themſelves and the diſtreſſed Iriſh, Submittees upon Articles of War, and others who are to have a certain proportion of their estates by the Act for the ſetling of</hi> Ireland, <hi>held forth in the year</hi> 1652. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to uſe their own words, They <hi>humbly ſhow, That the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners upon confidence of enjoying the Benefit of ſeveral Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Articles of War held forth unto them by Authority of this Parliament, &amp;c. did readily ſubject and put their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, Lives and Fortun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s as in a ſecure Sanctuary under the protection of this Commonwealth, having ever ſince walked peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and in due conformity to the Government, without the leaſt defection therein; That ſince the interruption given to the ſitting of this Parliament in the year 1653. no Christian Nation can parallel the ſufferings of the petitioners, &amp;c. which render the petitioners as fit Objects of your Honours piety, juſtice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as any who may challenge your protection. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Petitioners withered hopes, and former confidence, being a freſh revived by your Honours return to the management of the preſent Government, and their propenſions ſo great to peace and quietneſſe, that rather than ravel into the ſettlement, They do</hi> willingly <hi>acquieſce in the Tranſplantation, albeit it was not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by any legal power, as not being derived from your Honours.</hi> Soon after in the ſame Petition follow theſe words: <hi>They do apprehend that contrary to your Honours pious intentions mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested in the ſaid Act for ſettling of Ireland, they may be postponed or neglected, unleſs provided for in the Act of ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now to be establiſhed: And therefore the Petitioners humbly pray, &amp;c.</hi> This Petition was delivered by the ſaid two Agents for the Iriſh Papiſts at the door of the Houſe of Commons in <hi>England,</hi> and entered by the Clerk of the <hi>Rump.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38538:12"/>
               <p>The other petition was in writing, and ſubſcribed <hi>Robert Talbot, Garret Moor:</hi> the Title of it is, <hi>To the ſupreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c. Supplications humbly tendered by Sir</hi> Robert Talbot <hi>Bar. and</hi> Garret Moor <hi>Eſquire, for and on the behalf of themſelves and the diſtreſſed Roman Catholicks of</hi> Ireland, <hi>in order to be therein relieved by the Act of Settlement now to be paſſed.</hi> Their ſecond Supplication in this petition is ſet down in theſe words, viz. <hi>That the Eſtates aſſigned unto the Petitioners in the Province of</hi> Connaught <hi>and Country of</hi> Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>be</hi> confirm'd <hi>unto them.</hi> The third Supplication in the ſaid petition is in theſe words, viz. <hi>That the Decrees obtained by any of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners purſuant to the Articles and Qualifications be put in a way of ſatisfaction and for the time paſt put in equal condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with others who have had the benefit of their Decrees.</hi> The fourth Supplication of this petition is expreſſed in theſe words, viz. <hi>That there having been no time limited by this Parliament for the Petitioners to enter and proſecute the claims according to their reſpective Qualifications, and the interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given to the ſitting thereof ſoon after the Act of Settlement, having hindred many from doing the ſame; and that others through abſence, poverty, and the ſhort ſitting of the Court for the adjudication of Claims, appointed ſince the ſaid Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, could not do it, That a farther time be allowed unto ſuch to enter and proſecute (as aforeſaid) their Claims.</hi> The fifth Supplication is expreſſed in theſe words, viz <hi>That ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Petitioners are able to make appear their conſtant good affection and adherence to the Common-wealth, for whom a competent time to be allowed to make out the ſame, is humbly ſupplicated, and that theſe and ſuch of the Petitioners as have already done the ſame, may have the benefit held forth unto them by the Act for ſettling of</hi> Ireland.</p>
               <p>Theſe expreſſions being <hi>verbatim</hi> in the ſaid two petitions, I ſhall only obſerve from thence what follows, 1. The perſons who preſented theſe Requeſts to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP,</hi> did it not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for themſelves, but for the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in whoſe behalf they own themſelves to be Sollicitors. 2. Thoſe two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38538:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gentlemen (their publick Agents) were perſons of too much knowledge and diſcretion to have done any thing, eſpecially of ſo high a nature as this, for ſo great a body of people, without ſufficient power from themſelves ſo to do. 3. That theſe their Agents Addreſſes to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> were by allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and command from themſelves, needs not better to be proved, than by the Iriſh Papiſts ever ſince continuing thoſe their two Agents in publick employment for them, even to this day.</p>
               <p>4. To that very <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> by whoſe immediate Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the horrideſt of Murthers was acted, they ſcruple not to make their application, and even by the ſtile of the ſupreme authority the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and that twice. If P. W. ſhould ſay they were neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to petition, and that their petition would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without it were ſo directed, I anſwer, No conſequence of their ſuffering could be ſo great, as the guilt of owning the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> by the twice before mentioned Titles. The ſingle Advocate of the Iriſh Papiſts, viz. P. W. layes it as a guilt upon all the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that ſome of them fought under one of the Regicides to recover their own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and puniſh the guilt of the firſt Rebellion, and their often violation of their Articles; and yet their publick Agents in behalf of all the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> own all thoſe Regicides to be that ſupreme Authority.</p>
               <p>5. But if the Conſciences of the Iriſh Papiſts were harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed enough to run into a certain ſin, but in the expectancy of an uncertain advantage, why yet in their printed petition did they uſe theſe guilty expreſſions, viz. <hi>They did readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and put their CONSCIENCES, Lives and Fortunes as in a ſecure Sanctuary under the protection of that Commonwealth.</hi> Though if they would petition, they may ſay there was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to ſtile the RUMP, the Supreme authority; yet ſure they cannot ſay there was a neceſſity in the body of the petition to inſert ſuch criminal words: therefore ſince the <hi>Body of the Petition</hi> is <hi>more</hi> than conſonant to the Title of it, it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to believe, the Title they gave the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP,</hi> was as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38538:13"/> voluntary as the expreſſions with which they treat them. If they would but make his Sacred Majeſty, what in print they acknowledged the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> was to them, viz. <hi>A ſecure Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary to put their Conſciences, Lives and Fortunes in;</hi> if what is paſt could not be remedied, yet the miſchiefs to come might perhaps be prevented.</p>
               <p>6. But as if the immediate before mentioned reſpects to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> had not been ſufficient, they pay them others, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in theſe words, viz. <hi>Their withered hopes and former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidences are afreſh revived by the R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPS return to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Government, under which their propenſions to peace and quietneſs are ſo great, that they willingly ACQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SECE in the TRANSPLANTATION.</hi> Would they be but as joyfull for his Sacred Majeſties reſtauration, as they ſay they were for the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPS,</hi> and had they been as willing to expreſs their propenſity to the peace and quietneſs of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, under his Majeſties undoubted authority, as under the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPS</hi> uſurped power, P. W. had been exempt from the Guilts of writing and printing his Letter, and I from the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of anſwering it. The Iriſh Papiſts are not only content to declare, <hi>They willingly acquieſce in the Tranſplantation;</hi> but to heighten the merit of that performance, they add theſe words, viz. <hi>Albeit it was not executed by any legal power:</hi> yet had they ſtop'd there, thoſe their laſt words had been true, and ſure the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP</hi> would have had arrogancy enough to have aſſumed to themſelves without an explanation from the petitioners, that thereby was meant, what their Agents poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſay in the immediate next following words, viz <hi>As not derived from your Honours.</hi> Though the Iriſh Papiſts in their ingagements, nay Oaths to others, are not without their <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations</hi> and <hi>Mental reſervations,</hi> &amp;c. yet to the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP;</hi> when they might have left themſelves, (as to the laſt expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) to a fair explanation, they voluntarily caſt it behind them, in theſe clear words, <hi>As not derived from your Honors.</hi> Thoſe which now pretend to ſuch Loyalty to His Majeſty, voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſs, <hi>No execution was legal that was not derived from the R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MP,</hi> is not this implicitely, if not explicitely, an own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38538:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the Iriſh Papiſts the legality of the RUMPS power, even in the bloody Murther of his Sacred Majeſty, that being derived from thoſe the Iriſh Papiſts call <hi>Their Honours.</hi> But it is no wonder, that thoſe to whom the Iriſh Papiſts did <hi>readily ſubject themſelves and put their Conſciences, lives and fortunes as into a ſecure Sanctuary,</hi> ſhould have ſo much plainneſſe, kindneſs and obedience for them. May we not too from thence inferr, till they conſider his Sacred Majeſty, as they profeſs'd they conſidered the RUMP, his Majeſty may not well expect from them that ready Subjection and propenſity to peace, which in their ſaid Addreſſes they promiſed to thoſe Uſurpers.</p>
               <p>7. Obſerve, all this is ſaid and done ſince the peace of 1648. yea part of it, and that the moſt criminal too, but ſome few moneths before his Majeſties bleſſed Reſtauration; with what face could the Iriſh Papiſts by the ſame Agents plead for the Articles of peace before his Majeſty, as inviolable obſervers of them; who but a few weeks before owned the RUMP for the Supreme Authority: owned that they readily did ſubject and put their Conſciences, Lives and Fortunes, as in a ſecure Sanctuary, under their protection: owned their withered hopes and former confidence was afreſh reviv'd by the RUMP'S return to the management of the Government: owned their propenſions to peace and quietneſſe under the RUMP to be ſo great, that as one evidence thereof, they willingly did acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in the Tranſplantation; with theſe ſuperlative expreſſions, Albeit it was not executed by any legal power, as not being derived from their Honours. The very Murtherers of his late Majeſty of glorious memory are the elected Sanctuary of the Iriſh Papiſts, not only for their Lives and Fortunes, but even for their <hi>CONSCIENCES</hi> alſo. That bloody power which made the Royal Line of <hi>England,</hi> and all good Subjects of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ſo long wither, is by their return to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that onely which makes the hopes of the Iriſh Papiſts to revive and ſpring. That power is by the Iriſh Papiſts owned to be the only Legal one, by which all our Laws and Liberties were cut up even by the very Roots. Were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng but this to make them forfeit the Articles they ſo plead for, it were but too
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38538:14"/> much; if this be their obſervance of their Recognition of his Majeſty, though the Pope may abſolve them, God will not. Sure P. W. cannot prove any one of the Proteſtants, whoſe whole number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo calumniates, to be ſo criminal, as I have proved even the Generality of the Iriſh Papiſts to be, in this one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; <hi>I bate him many others.</hi> And doubtleſs 'twas a leſs ſin the ſeduced Proteſtants to ſubmit for a while to him who caſt down thoſe Engliſh Murtherers, and helped them againſt theſe Iriſh Murtherers, than readily to ſubject their Conſciences, lives and Fortunes to thoſe Parricides, yea to own them as their Secure Sanctuary for All, and ſo pathetically to exult, in their ſecond uſurpation.</p>
               <p>8. In the many forementioned paſſages, both of the written and printed petition, they preſſe for the Confirmation of the Tranſplantation, and the benefit of the Rules for adjudging of Qualifications, and make the granting thereof to be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ects of the RUMP'S Piety, Juſtice and Compaſſion. The Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are pleaſed to beg that Grant, as an act of piety, juſtice and compaſſion in the RUMP, which his Sacred Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, (and much more to the advantage of the Iriſh) P. W. calls an Injuſtice. And in the 6. and 7. Paragraphs of the ſaid written petition, they ſet forth that <hi>ſeveral of the Petitioners are able to make appear their conſtant good affection and adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Commonwealth, that ſome have already actually done it:</hi> And in effect, That the number of thoſe <hi>ſo adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and of constant good affection to the Commonwealth</hi> was ſo great, that they ſue even for a longer time than had been allowed, for the proving thereof; they being ſo many, that they were ſtreightned in time to make out that truth.</p>
               <p>There are other clear obſervations and inferences which I could make out of thoſe two petitions, which I decline; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough having been ſaid to evince what I promiſed to prove upon this Head: and I have much behind to anſwer, to which I haſten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Guilt of the Coporations in part inſtanced.</head>
               <p>The 2. ſpecial Caſe concerns the Iriſh Corporations which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38538:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> P. W. with his uſual confidence determines, <hi>cannot be excluded on any account that may ſtand with his Majeſties Gracious Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; nor can there be any reaſons of State which may accord with a good Conſcience to exclude them;</hi> yet he confeſſeth with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, <hi>That two or three of them deſerved puniſhment, and</hi> Limerick <hi>a ſevere one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Corporations of <hi>Ireland</hi> that P. W. mentions were ſo notoriouſly guilty in overthrowing the foundation of that peace wreſted from his Majeſty, that it ſeems ſtrange how any one can be found to plead for them, eſpecially to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> who knows their actings. Their Education rendered them moſt able of any to know their duty; their Incorporation moſt capable of any to deliberate concerning their duty; their Fortifications and men moſt ſecure to diſcharge their duty; yet theſe above all other perſons and places, put forth with greateſt Arguments of Choice and Freedom, the higheſt acts of Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Rebellion. The evidences whereof amount to much more than P. W.'s <hi>peradventure,</hi> and the Subject reacheth much far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than P. W's <hi>two or three Corporations,</hi> it being the general practiſe of all ſuch, into which his Majeſties L. Lieutenant deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red admiſſion. P. W. confeſſeth, <hi>That</hi> Limerick <hi>deſerved a ſevere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>niſhment,</hi> and certainly the demerit muſt be great, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torts this Confeſſion even from their Advocate; nor was their Crime leſs than <hi>laeſae Majestatis,</hi> for they inſolently oppoſed the admiſſion of his Majeſties Viceroy: though 1. their Maior had invited him, 2. <hi>Iretons</hi> ſtorm threatned their wrack, 3. the L. Lieutenant offered to ſteer that Veſſel, and to adventure his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Fortune in the ſame bottome with them. But ſurely if <hi>Limerick</hi> deſerves many ſtripes, <hi>Gallway</hi> and <hi>Waterford</hi> propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally to their crimes deſerve more. <hi>Gallway</hi> after the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of 1648. (ſo much and groundleſly pleaded) 1. ſearched (to uſe his Graces own words) <hi>with force and armes for the L. Lievtenant, as if they judged him a Traitor.</hi> 2. They treated with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to be Protector of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as if they judged themſelves Lords of all. 3. They refuſed to admit any Garriſon commiſſionated by his Majeſtie's authority, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred that Town (as if they eſteem'd themſelves a Free State) without conſulting the Marqueſs of <hi>Claurickard</hi> then L. Deputy,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38538:15"/> though reſident within few miles thereof, and though he were of P. W's own Nation and Religion. But I will not ſay that even thoſe double Tyes were leſs powerfull to beget a reſpect for him, than his repreſenting the Kings perſon, and his own worth, were incitements to P. W's Countreymen ſo highly to affront him. <hi>Waterford</hi> likewiſe after thoſe Articles of 1648. deny'd a paſſage to the L. Lieutenant and his Army, though at that time his Lordſhip was ſtrengthened with the conjunction of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> Forces, in purſuit of the Enemy, who were weakned by a long Winter March, Multiplicity of Garriſons, want of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, and ſickneſs of the Souldiers; nay offered himſelf to become an hoſtage, and to commit the Army to anothers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; yea ſo horrid was their perfidie, that when afterwards the L. Lieutenant and ſeven more were occaſionally received into that City, the Citizens combin'd either to take away his life, or deliver him up priſoner to the Uſurpers; for the prevention whereof, he was forc'd ſuddenly and ſecretly to withdraw thence.</p>
               <p>What falſehood will P. W. be affraid to ſuggeſt to Strangers, &amp; what wickedneſs will he be affraid to patronize at home, when he ſhall dare thus to aſſert to the L. Lieutenant himſelf, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in print to the world, <hi>That no reaſons of State can accord with the dictates of a good Conſcience, to exclude theſe Corporations from the future capacity</hi> of repeating ſuch ſignal acts of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But P. W. as farther motives of favour to the ſaid Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, addes and ſayes, 1, <hi>The hand of God hath puniſhed them; 2. Some were faithfull among them; 3. The Engliſh Proteſtants are more criminal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>The hand of God hath puniſhed them:</hi> But that the Magiſtrate ſhould ſpare, becauſe God puniſhes, is a <hi>non ſequitur.</hi> Though the Lord ſent Hornets before <hi>Iſrael</hi> to drive out the <hi>Hivite</hi> and the <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ite</hi> and the <hi>Hittites;</hi> yet he commands <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> to deſtroy thoſe Nations, and their name from under Heaven.</p>
               <p>2. P. W. ſayes, <hi>There have been many faithfull Subjects in thoſe Towns, even in the most criminal of them; and God was ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r from involving the juſt in the deſtruction of the wicked Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38538:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> that if he could find there but ten just men, be would for their ſake pardon all the reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſin of Apoſtacy ſeems worſe in ſome reſpect than other ſins; and therefore on this ſin, <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, whom God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued from the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> though but for looking back to it, is immediately turned into a <hi>pillar of Salt.</hi> I heartily wiſh the Iriſh Apoſtates would remember <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though God would not involve the righteous in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Wicked, but delivered juſt <hi>Lot;</hi> yet he tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him into <hi>Zoar,</hi> and condemned <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrae</hi> with an overthrow, making them an Example to thoſe that after ſhould live ungodly. Even ſo his Majeſty hath taken care for the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, in his Gracious Declaration, without juſtifying the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for the Innocent has provided a <hi>Zoar,</hi> whether their Souls may eſcape and live.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Since <hi>P. W.</hi> profeſſeth his thoughts to be far from deſiring to obſtruct the ſecuring the peace of the Countrey; let him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how adviſeable it is to put a Sword into a Madmans hand, or to capacitate ſuch rebellious Spirits to hurt themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and others.</p>
               <p>Since <hi>Limerick,</hi> notwithſtanding the hand of God, and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of good, <hi>deſerved a ſevere puniſhment;</hi> and ſince <hi>Gallway</hi> and <hi>Waterford</hi> are not leſs deſerving; ought not thoſe Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and their Advocate rather to acknowledge his Majeſties gracious indulgence and mercy, in remitting the ſeverity of the Laws: than to exclaim thus inſolently againſt his Royal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings <hi>as unjuſt, unequal, and ſuch as cannot accord with a good Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Guilt of Engliſh Proteſtants and Iriſh Papiſts compared.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, P. W. returns to his former Compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Iriſh Papiſts and the Engliſh Proteſtants; and in proſecution thereof urgeth, 1. <hi>That the worst of the Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts were never Regicides; 2. That they fought againſt ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38538:16"/> men, when</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and the Protestants of</hi> Ireland <hi>deſerted the Royal Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt, <hi>That the Iriſh Papiſts are not Regicides;</hi> let it be conſidered, That the Doctrine of Regicide is common in the Romiſh Schools, and the practiſe in their Courts.</p>
               <p>2. That to touch the Annointing, is virtually to touch the Annointed. Take away the <hi>Regalia,</hi> and in effect you take away the King. The Iriſh Papiſts were ſo guilty hereof, that they not only uſurped all the Royal peculiars, but alſo ſet up a Government diſtinct from, and oppoſite to his Majeſtie's in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly; yea therein they Enacted, <hi>viz. That no Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Government or Juriſdiction ſhould be aſſumed, kept or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in</hi> Ireland, <hi>or in any Province or County thereof, other than what ſhould be approved or instituted by their General Aſſembly.</hi> Had the Devil had leave to touch <hi>Job</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he would not have ſpared him, when he touched <hi>all that was his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Did not the Iriſh Papiſts, diſtruſt, diſobey, oppoſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate the L. Lieutenant, and abſolutely diſclaim his Majeſties Authority in him; did they not conſpire to Murther Him, or which is worſe (if worſe can be) to deliver him to the worſt of Murtherers? Surely thoſe who dealt thus with ſuch a Servant, if the Son had been ſent to them, would not have ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled his Murther, that the Inheritance might wholly be theirs.</p>
               <p>As to the 2. That <hi>when</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of</hi> Ireland <hi>wholly deſerted the Royal C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe, the Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists fought againſt the Regicides in defence of his Majeſties right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. It is no leſs calumnious than falſe, to charge <hi>England, Scotland &amp; the Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland <hi>to have wholly deſerted the Royal Cauſe:</hi> and it is amazing to conſider how any Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt (I am loath to ſay Rebel) dare thus by a Letter even to the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and printed paper to the whole World, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to have wholly deſerted the Royal Cauſe: what may not Foreigners credit againſt us abroad, if P. W. dare thus to charge us at home?</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:38538:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>But a Narrative of the matter of Fact is the cleareſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to refute this Slander: wherein let <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sootland</hi> anſwer for themſelves; (if any Anſwer ſeem neceſſary to ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable a falſehood) and let the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> excuſe my zeal, if I urge ſome clear inſtances (though I pretermit many) for their vindication.</p>
               <p>Thoſe w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> P. W. ſlanders with having deſerted the royal Cauſe, when the Iriſh Papiſts fought againſt the Regicides in defence of his Majeſties Rights, were even the very firſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed his Majeſty, my L. Lieutenant alſo at the head of them; and that duty was performed by the Proteſtant army in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Munster,</hi> the ſame year in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> by giving the Iriſh Papiſts ſome conſiderable defeats, the ſaid Papiſts were reduced to a real neceſſity of ſubmitting to his Majeſty, which yet they but ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did. But poſſibly P. W. was at that time ſo buſie in preparing thoſe <hi>Articles of Peace</hi> which were to fetter his Majeſty, that he had not leaſure to hear how his Proteſtant Subjects freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd him. It is alſo undenyably true, that a conſiderable Body of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> under the L. Lieutenant, though mingled with the Iriſh Papiſts, fought conſtantly againſt the Regicides, nay after the ſaid Iriſh Papiſts would have been Regicides themſelves, at leaſt ſo far ſuch as conſpiring to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Majeſty <hi>in effigie</hi> at <hi>Waterford, &amp;c.</hi> did amount unto, and never declin'd that Quarrell, till by the infidelity of their Accuſers, they were not only diſabled to proſecute it, but as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of themſelves have confeſt, were reduc'd at laſt, even for the preſervation of their lives, to keep as ſtrict Guards againſt the Iriſh Papiſts as againſt <hi>Cromwell.</hi> All which his Grace having found was but too true, he withdrew himſelf at laſt out of the Kingdom and permitted thoſe Proteſtants to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Iriſh: Therefore let any unbyaſſed perſon judge whether the Iriſh Papiſts or all the Proteſtants were wholly the Deſerters of the Royal Cauſe; or which of them fought longeſt againſt the Regicides: if the inſolence and diſloyalty of the Iriſh Papiſts were ſuch, even when <hi>Cromwell</hi> was at their gates, what would it not have been without that Curb. But I ſee though <hi>P. W.</hi> remembers wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhould not, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he can forget what he ſhould remember.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38538:17"/>
               <p>In the years 1641. and 1642. the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi> not onely fought as his Majeſties Subjects, but by his Command and with his Commiſſion againſt the Iriſh Rebels; in the year 1643. a Ceſſation was concluded by his Majeſties Authoritie, and the Iriſh engaged by Articles; both Engliſh and Iriſh by duty, to tranſport their Armies to <hi>England</hi> for his Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. The Engliſh did it, the Iriſh only made a ſhow (till the Engliſh were gone) of doing of it, and then plotted and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the deſtruction of the few Engliſh remaining in <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> whereby the Lord of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> who then commanded in that Province by the Kings Commiſſion; and the Engliſh with him were neceſſitated to ſtand on their own defence, yet this is the firſt pretence which the Iriſh Papiſts make, that the Engliſh Proteſtants deſerted the Royal Cauſe. Can even Malice it ſelf judge, the Proteſtants deſigned the deſerting of the Kings ſervice, when they ſent their Armie to the King, by which onely they were capable of diſſerving him: nay ſent it in that very Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time, wherein they had as much cauſe to fear the ruine of themſelves and Families, from the often Violations of the Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation by the Iriſh Papiſts, after that Ceſſation was made, as from their inhumanities before. But yet, when his Majeſties Service required it, though the anſwering thereof, by tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Armies into <hi>England,</hi> threatned more than a probable ruine to them at home from the Iriſh Papiſts, who then delayed, and indeed never after would ſend an Army to the King into <hi>England;</hi> yet the Proteſtants did not ſo much as heſitate, but chearfully expoſed themſelves to the danger, to pay the duty, and receive the honour of their obedience.</p>
               <p>The ſame Infidelity and Treachery which <hi>Munſter,</hi> and the parts more remote firſt experienced, the L. Lieutenant and the Proteſtants with him at <hi>Dublin</hi> at laſt taſted: and his Grace was thereby compelled in the year 1647. (with his Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, if not Order) to reſign <hi>Dublin</hi> and all the adjoyning Garriſons in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hands of the Parliament, which is the ſecond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion for this ſlander.</p>
               <p>On theſe occaſions the Engliſh Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> (not by Choyce but Neceſſity, (and a neceſſity onely created by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38538:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Iriſh Papiſts themſelves) not by the Proteſtants own private acts, but the neceſſitated Acts of thoſe that were ſet over them by his Majeſties authority) came into the Stream, with the violence whereof they confeſs themſelves afterwards hurried into ſuch miſcarriages as made their hearts ake; yet (they hope) leſs criminal than thoſe in the Iriſh Rebellion, or to any degree of Apoſtacy, which deſerves the ſcandal that <hi>P. W.</hi> layes on them, of wholly deſerting the Royal Cauſe.</p>
               <p>For 1. Notwithſtanding the violent endeavours of both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Anabaptiſts, not many of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> have declined the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in her greateſt Tryals; whoſe principles are not only moſt conſonant to Truth, but alſo moſt uſefull and duti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull to the Royal Cauſe: and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were oppoſed moſt by the two Extremes. So that Old Proteſtants in the Anabaptiſts Dialect, was the ſame with Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, and by them the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> were dealt with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. And 2. as the principles, ſo the practiſes of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants vindicate their loyalty. 1. They ſubmitted this Kingdom to his Majeſty; not as <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the concurrence of the General and General Officers, but without them, nay againſt them. 2. Though they ſaw the difficulty of that attempt, and foreſaw the hazard from Anabaptiſts (who then in chief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Army in <hi>Ireland</hi>) if they ſucceeded not; and from Iriſh Papiſt pretenders (whoſe neceſſities had driven them to ſerve themſelves by his Majeſty in <hi>Flanders</hi>) if they ſucceeded; yet were they early (if not the firſt) and free without Articling in the duty of their Submiſſions. And leaſt P. W. who ſaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many things that are not true, ſhould deny this, which is ſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally true, I will cite the undenyable Teſtimony of his Sacred Majeſty himſelf, which follows in theſe words in the 2. page of his Majeſties gracious Declaration for the Settlement of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: We acknowledge that our good Subjects of the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland <hi>have born a very good part in procuring this happineſs, that they were EARLY in their dutifull Addreſſes to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and made the ſame profeſſions of a reſolution to return to their Duty and Obedience to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, during the time of Our being beyond the Seas, which they have ſince ſo EMINENTLY made good and put in practiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38538:18"/>
               <p>Here is not only a profeſſion of duty, but a making of it good, and putting it in practiſe. Here is not only an early owning of His Majeſties Authority, but an owning it when he was deveſted from the actual exerciſe of it, and that too (as to <hi>Ireland</hi>) by the <hi>Iriſh Papists.</hi> And this is alſo the firſt fruits of the Proteſtants having recovered the power of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that with no leſs hazard than loyalty.</p>
               <p>3. To make the Diſcrimination yet clearer: The Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts at firſt murther'd and fought againſt his Majeſties good Subjects, to take from him his Crown. The Proteſtants of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> fought againſt his Enemies to reſtore him to it. The Papiſts of <hi>Ireland</hi> we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>ſeemingly good Subjects,</hi> but to become more dangerous Rebels. But the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> if ſeemingly Rebels, were ſuch, but to become more uſeful Subjects. The laſt action of the Iriſh Papiſts, when they had the power, was to expell His Majeſties Authority, with circumſtances as wicked as the very ſin; but the firſt action of the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, when they were in power, was to reſtore His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Authority, with circumſtances almoſt as dutifull as the Action it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Not to hold a candle longer to the Sun, I will but inſtance one other experiment, and againſt an experiment there is no arguing; and the inſtance of this experiment is even in the very caſe now controverted, and in which alſo my L. Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> himſelf was the Judge. In the year 1650. when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> came in Queſtion, which were the worſt, the Iriſh Papiſts, or the ſeduced Proteſtants. He permitted all thoſe worthy Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants which till then had ſerved under him, to come off to the reſt of the Proteſtants, though then headed by <hi>Ireton</hi> himſelf; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming them ſafer with that real Regicide ſo accompanied, than with thoſe <hi>pretended Antiregicides, ſo principled.</hi> Certainly he eſteems thoſe leſs ill to whom he ſends his Friends, than from whom he ſends them. If ſo wiſe and ſo faithfull a Servant to his Majeſty, as the L. Lieutenant is, had had any hope that the Iriſh Papiſts, would ever have return'd to their Loyalty, doubtleſs he would never have ſent away from them, ſo many pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful helpers of it, and friends unto it: and if his Grace had not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38538:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> had more than hopes that the Engliſh Proteſtants would have return'd to their obedience as ſoon as they had got the power of doing it, he would never have ſent his friends unto them. The Wiſdom of his Grace's foreſight has been happily juſtified in the Reſult. For all the Proteſtants which then came off, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently inſtrumental and concurring in the duty of accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that bleſſed Event. I dare as truly as confiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ſay, the moſt of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> only ſerved under the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, but to bring the Iriſh Papiſts to thoſe terms which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the force of Engliſh ſwords they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would never have been brought unto. The ancient and modern often breaches o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th which the Iriſh Papiſts were guilty of, made it too evident to many of the Proteſtants, that nothing could bind them but <hi>ſteel,</hi> and <hi>iron.</hi> The truth of both theſe po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itions is clearly read in that iſſue which the providence of God has effected. However the once ſeduced Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> are willing to take ſhame to themſelves, and give glory to God, in con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſing their Guilt ſuch, (though not by cauſing, yet by complying with the late Uſurpation, though to a good end) that they readily acknowledg they owe their Lives and Eſtates wholly to His Majeſties Grace and indulgence; and will be more joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to employ both in the honor and duty of his ſervice, than now they are in having received both from his mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For 'tis fitter to diſcharge obligations, than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract them. The lively ſenſe the once ſeduced Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> have of their failings, and of His Majeſties Clemency, ſo juſtly humbles them, that they can take no pleaſure to recriminate others, farther than by ſhewing the Injuſtice of P. W's. compariſons; which they are more troubled he gave them a riſe to do, than after the riſe was given they were troubled to find out what fully has done it. But in regard the Iriſh Papiſts in all their Diſcourſes, as well as their papers, pretend to the <hi>defence of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Right;</hi> it ſeems even neceſſary, by way of anſwer to the other branch of this propoſition, to rub up their memories. 1. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in 1641 the Iriſh Papiſts unprovoak'd (1) <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, (2) robbed</hi> the Proteſtants of more perſonal eſtate, than
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38538:19"/> the Fee-ſimple of all the forfeited Lands in Ireland is worth; (3) in a few Months <hi>murthered</hi> about two hundred thouſand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents; (4) with a ſin next to Blaſphemy, as now they pretend his Majeſties <hi>defenſe,</hi> ſo then they pretended his <hi>Authority.</hi> The <hi>pretending</hi> whereof having been ſo horrid a ſin, (for it was no leſs than to have intitled his then Sacred Majeſty to all their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd crimes, nay to have made him the Author of them) I think it a duty to the memory of that Glorious <hi>MARTYR,</hi> to preſent the Reader in this place with what will clearly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince their malice therein to be as great, as his then Majeſties Innocence; and nothing can better illuſtrate the vaſtneſſe of <hi>This,</hi> but by proving 'tis a parallel to <hi>That.</hi> I could inſtance many ſignal and clear evidences of this <hi>Truth,</hi> beſides that memorable one which follows: But ſince I have in moſt part of my Anſwer made uſe of their own Writings, and prints to make out their guilt: in this very particular I will purſue that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and only cite the preamble of their own Remonſtrance, delivered by the Lord Viſcount <hi>Gormanston,</hi> Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Talbot</hi> Baronet, to His Majeſties Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners at the Town of <hi>Trim</hi> in the County of <hi>Meath,</hi> on the 17. of <hi>March</hi> 1642. In which Remonſtrance of Grievances (for ſo they call it) after they have taken notice that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had authorized Commiſſioners to hear what they ſhould ſay, or pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pound, theſe very words follow, <hi>viz. Which your Majeſties gracious and Princely Favour we find to be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with theſe words, viz. Albeit we do extremely deteſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dious Rebellion which the Recuſants of</hi> Ireland <hi>have, without ground or colour, raiſed against us, Our Crown and Dignity.</hi> Word which deſerve to be written with a <hi>Beam of the Sun,</hi> as eternal mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments of his <hi>Majeſties Juſtice,</hi> and their guilt; nor were they ſpoken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a corner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut ſpoken under the Great Seal, and even in that Commiſſion which thoſe Falſe-accuſers were to ſee and hear read, and by thoſe expreſſions they were ſufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rovoked to have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaded that Authority they ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ely pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended, had they had the leaſt ſhadow for that black ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umny. In theſe Royal expreſſions alſo (if at leaſt the Iriſh Papiſts have the modeſty (I bate them the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38538:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> to acknowledge the King was a fitter Judge of their Crimes, then they themſelves were) the actings of the chief Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> when that horrid Rebellion brake out, are fully vindicated: for the ſaid Iriſh were ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provoked unto it by thoſe, that no leſs a Teſtimony than the word of that great, juſt and wiſe Prince proves, they had no ground, nay not ſo much as a colour for it.</p>
               <p>2. In the year 1646. and after a peace concluded with them, they attempted, by a Treachery not to be parallel'd by any but themſelves, to cut off the Lord Lieutenant and Army with him, who marched out of <hi>Dublin</hi> on ſecurity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of that peace.</p>
               <p>3. The ſame year, the <hi>Council and Congregation of the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Catholicks of Ireland,</hi> obliged their General <hi>Preſton</hi> by a ſolemn Oath, in theſe very words, <hi>viz. To exerciſe all acts of Hoſtility against the L. Marqueſs of Ormond</hi> by name, <hi>and his party; and to help, adviſe with counſel, and aſſiſt in that ſervice the L. General of</hi> Ulſter <hi>employed in the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Oath is a fruitful <hi>Theme</hi> to declaim upon, but I will l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mit my obſervations upon it, only to theſe following particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. 1. Leaſt any ſhould doubt they are his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; leaſt any of themſelves ſhould repent the ſin of not having been ſuch, they ſwear (that they may raiſe their crimes above pardon) to exerciſe <hi>all acts of Hoſtility againſt his Majeſty,</hi> in the perſon of that noble Lord who had then, as now, the high honour to repreſent him; if <hi>killing</hi> be an act of <hi>Hoſtility,</hi> they in this Oath ſwear to kill him; if this be not actual Regicide, I am ſure 'tis not their fault that it is not. This horrid Oath takes off all diſguiſes, and makes their ſin as viſible as great. And if ſuch a Crime be capable of acceſſion, it did contract it by the ſame perſons engaging private<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, about the ſame time, (as I have been aſſured by an undeniable Teſtimony) That he would <hi>ſerve the King,</hi> which he afterwards endeavour'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe only by ſaying, <hi>His Army was not Nuntio-proof.</hi> By which it appears indiſputably whether the Iriſh Papiſts are Subject to the <hi>King,</hi> or to the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38538:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>(2) Inſtead of repenting and making amends for the late violated peace in the year 1646, they ſwear to <hi>deſtroy</hi> him, with whom they had made it.</p>
               <p>(3) This Oath reduc'd the taker of it to a ſad Dilemma, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Rebellion or perjury.</p>
               <p>(4) This Oath evidences that nothing is ſo powerful with the Iriſh Papiſts, as to <hi>destroy his Majeſties</hi> Government; ſince the uniting of the old Iriſh Papiſts and the old Engliſh Papiſts, which the Pope himſelf could not effect: the dethroning of his Sacred Majeſty has accompliſh'd. They that could never agree in any thing elſe, agree in this, and it is made the very bond of their iniquity. I will ſay no more on this ſubject, but that <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> could be friends, when it was to crucify <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. In the year 1647. from <hi>Kilkenny Jan.</hi> 18. the Popiſh Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons of the <hi>confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Catholicks of Ireland</hi> employ Commiſſioners to <hi>Rome, France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> to invite a forreign power into <hi>Ireland,</hi> particularly to <hi>Rome</hi> their titular Biſhop of <hi>Ferns</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Plunket</hi> Eſq; (who was Knighted by the Pope for his good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice therein, and is now one of the confident Advocates for the Iriſh Papiſts as <hi>defenders of his Majeſties Rights,</hi> and againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> as <hi>deſerters of the Royal cauſe</hi>) theſe, I ſay were authoriſed to declare, <hi>viz. That they raiſed arms for the freedom of the Catholick Religion;</hi> which are their own very words in the third Article of thoſe their Inſtructions.</p>
               <p>In their Remonſtrance in the beginning of the Rebellion, whatever they ſaid neceſſitated ſome few diſcontents to take up arms, then they took off the vail, and poſitively ſaid, <hi>That they raiſed arms for the freedom of the Catholick Religion.</hi> Certainly if ever they may be believed to ſpeak true, it is when they ſpeak to the POPE; and if ever any thing may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be the voice of all the Iriſh Papiſts, it is when the Popiſh Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons of the Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ederate Catholicks ſpeak in one Aſſembly. What is meant by the <hi>Freedom of the Catholick Religion</hi> has been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically expounded by the profeſſours of it in <hi>Ireland;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38538:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> affirmatively, that thoſe which are of it, ſhould enjoy the publick and undiſturbed exerciſe thereof themſelves; but Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively, to be an excluſion of the publick, if not private, exerciſe of the true Religion. Many inſtances I could preſent the Reader of this, but I ſhall only ſet down two: The 1. is <hi>Dean York</hi> a reverend Miniſter of Gods word, during his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence at <hi>Gallway,</hi> was not allowed to pay the laſt duties of Chriſtian burial to thoſe Proteſtants which died in that Town; but was forced to bury them, nay his own children, privately in his Garden. The 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is, That my L. Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> though owned by the Iriſh papiſts to be the Kings L. Lieutenant and conſequently repreſenting his Sacred Majeſties perſon, was ſtill denied the uſe of ſo much as one Church or Chappel, wherever the ſaid Papiſts had the power; nay one of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the Iriſh PAPISTS, now living, told my L. Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> That if the King in perſon came into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he ſhould not be allowed by them One Church to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate his Devotions in: to whom his Grace made a return, proportionate to the diſloyalty of that Declaration, and part of that return being prophetical, and ſince fulfilled, I ſhall here inſert the words, <hi>viz, I hope to live to ſee all of that mind to be without one Church in</hi> Ireland <hi>to ſay Maſs in.</hi> By theſe two inſtances it is evident, That the direct meaning of thoſe words, <hi>The Freedom of the Catholick Religion,</hi> is no other than the total baniſhing out of this Kingdom the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Religion eſtabliſhed in it, by truth it ſelf, and by the good and wholſom Laws of the Land.</p>
               <p>5. In another part of the third Article of the ſaid Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, theſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very words are inſerted, <hi>viz. The confederate Catholicks do intend that you let his Holyneſs know, their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to inſiſt upon ſuch Conceſſions and Agreements in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and for the ſecurity thereof as his Holineſs ſhall approve of, and be ſatisfied with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This palpably evinceth, that the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland</hi> being Subjects, or Rebels, depends wholly upon the Popes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: For let his Majeſty grant them what he will, yet his pretended Holineſs's approbation muſt be the rule by which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38538:21"/> only they will be bound. And this is made moſt evident by the words of the ninth Article in the ſaid Inſtructions, which follow in theſe words, <hi>viz. In caſe his Holineſs will not be pleaſed to deſcend to ſuch Conditions, as might be granted in matters of Religion, then you are to ſollicit for conſiderable aids, whereby to maintain a war, and to aſcertain and ſecure the ſame, &amp;c.</hi> And ſoon after in the ſame ninth Article, theſe words follow; <hi>viz. You are to make application to his Holineſs for his being Protector of this Kingdom; and by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al instance to endeavour his acceptance thereof, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Still the Pope is there King;</hi> and that he may be ſo almoſt in name as well as in power, they ſollicit him by ſpecial in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to accept that Title, under which he might act that power: ſo that it is not the <hi>Confederate Catholicks</hi> fault, if a <hi>PROTECTOR</hi> were not in <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries had ſet up one in <hi>England.</hi> Nay their Commiſſioners then ſent to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> were required in caſe of the <hi>Popes refuſal</hi> of being their Protector, to offer it to either of thoſe Kings, nay to any <hi>Popiſh Prince,</hi> from whom (to uſe their own words) they might have moſt conſiderable aids. In effect, they are willing any one ſhould govern them, but he who only had the Right to do it. But yet as becomes obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Sons of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope has the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the preemption.</p>
               <p>It appears the Iriſh Papiſts hang, as their faith in God, ſo their Loyalty to their Prince, on the Popes ſleeve; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is not probable that thoſe ſhould defend his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Right, over whom (1) a forreign Prince, (2) ſuch a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince as conſiders His Majeſty as an Heretick, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently an Enemy, hath full power; and (3) That power on the ſtrongeſt account, even that of Conſcience of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>In the year 1648. another peace was concluded with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Papiſts, but after that, they <hi>diſowned, diſobeyed, oppoſed, conſpired to murther,</hi> excommunicated, and baniſhed His <hi>Majesties Viceroy,</hi> as appears by the former inſtances.</p>
               <p>In ſum, when the power of <hi>Ireland</hi> was in the hands of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38538:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Iriſh Papists,</hi> they deſign'd and endeavour'd to betray it to Forreigners: But when in the hands of the <hi>Protestants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> they abſolutely, and without antecedent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſubmitted it and themſelves to His Sacred Majeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>As to their fighting againſt the Regicides.</head>
               <p>I anſwer, 1. Vitious extremes are not only oppoſite to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but alſo one to the other; <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Sectaries</hi> oppoſe each other, and both the Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>2. The Spaniard and the Dutch fought againſt the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, yet neither of them in the day of tryal, proved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves friends to his Majeſties Rights.</p>
               <p>3. 'Tis the Cauſe, not the ſuffering only, which makes the Martyr; 'tis not the fighting, but the ground and end of the fighting, which proves which is the good Subject, and of that, let even <hi>P. W.</hi> judge by the former inſtances.</p>
               <p>The laſt argument pretends to commutative Juſtice, and is uſher'd in by a compariſon and preoccupation.</p>
               <p>The former thrice preſſed way of compariſon, is yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded here again, but with leſs injuſtice here, than before; the compariſon before was between Papiſts and Proteſtants, here between Papiſts and Presbyterians, Anabaptiſts, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Fifth Monarchy men, Independents.</p>
               <p>To which I ſhall only ſay, Whatever tenents oppoſit to Regal power may be found among any Sectaries, are, if not learn'd from, I am ſure taught by the Romiſh Schools. Papiſts and Sectaries like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, are tyed by their tails, though their heads be divided; their way may ſeem contrary, but they all tend to the ſame end, the ruine of the Corn-field.</p>
               <p>As P. W. uſhers in his Arguments on one ſide with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon: ſo on the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a preoccupation, re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to the power of thoſe which he calls Adverſaries, and declareth it <hi>to be no greater than His Majesty is pleaſed to make it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the truth of this Declaration the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> freely conſent; profeſſing to the World, that though their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38538:22"/> Army is ſuch, as ſufficed to ſubdue the Iriſh Rebels when uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally confederated throughout the Kingdom, and ſupplyed by Foreigners with Money, Armes and Ammunition, and ſtrengthened with no leſſe than the Popes Bleſsing and Nuntio: yet their power conſiſts not in Armes or Armies, Fortifications or Men; but in Loyalty and Obedience to his Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Commiſsion and Authority; and is conſequently, as P. W. ſayes, <hi>no greater than his Majeſty is pleaſed to make it.</hi> And ſince this is the true ſtate of the Proteſtant, both Principle and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, As in truth it is, even their Adverſary being their Judge, 'tis likely therefore that P. W. declares they are his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, (for I believe his Friends are other gueſs men) But doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thoſe are fitteſt to be truſted with Power, who are no ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by it, even by their Enemies acknowledgements, than He which gives it, is willing to make it; than thoſe who never had power, but what they forc'd from his Majeſty; and who never employ'd that Power (the whole ſtream of their own actions being their Judges) but againſt that Sacred Majeſty from whom they wreſted it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Arguments following plead Juſtice, and that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice grounded on the Articles of 1648. and judged by the ſad conſequences threatned on the breach thereof, whether we regard men or God.</head>
               <p>Though concerning the Arrticles of 1648. enough hath been inſtanced already, yet to leave P. W. without occaſion of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, it will not be unfit to adde ſomewhat more here.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Contents of thoſe Articles are in themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, except in Caſe of Neceſſitie which hath no Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Condition of thoſe Articles whereon they were prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, if not onely founded, hath been often and intirely vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the Iriſh Papiſts.</p>
               <p>The Contents of thoſe Articles are unwarrantable, unleſs in Caſe of Neceſſity, becauſe they are contrary to an higher Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38538:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> according to the Rule both of publick and private Juſtice.</p>
               <p>1. His Majeſty at his Coronation, binds himſelf to God, to govern theſe Kingdoms according to their reſpective Laws; and let P. W. himſelf conſider, how agreeable it is to Law or publick Juſtice, that the Militia, Treaſury, an Army of fifteen thouſand Foot, two thouſand five hundred Horſe, of Iriſh Papiſts, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in effect the Legiſlative power it ſelf, ſhould be in the hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of twelve men to be choſen by Iriſh Papiſts; or that there ſhould be no alteration in <hi>England</hi> of what they in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould think fit to tranſmit to his Majeſty for the ſettlement of that Kingdom; or even that the Iriſh Rebels ſhould be pardoned without the conſent of Parliament, when his Majeſty in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſeventeenth year of his Reign, adjudged ſuch pardon before Conviction to be null and void; hereby even when they treated with his Majeſty concerning the Affairs of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, aſſuming the Legiſlative authority of it, by repealing the Statute made the 10. of <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. (commonly called <hi>Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings Law</hi>) and the explanatory Law thereof, in 3. &amp; 4. of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though hitherto they chiefly pleaded before his Sacred Majeſty in Council, but for ſo much benefit of the Articles of peace in 1648. as would reſtore them to their forfeited Eſtates: yet if they had prevailed therein, upon the ſcore of that plea, it muſt in conſequence have adjudged for them the benefit of all the other Articles as a Right. For if any of thoſe Articles are due to them by an Obligation of Juſtice, all are then d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to them by the ſame Obligation; and ſince, as appears by his Majeſties Gracious Declaration in Council, of the 30. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1660. that they have no right to any of their forfeited Eſtate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nor any title but what his Majeſties mercy and bounty hath vouchſafed to diverſe of them; it thence follows, That his Majeſty in Council has adjudged, They have no right to thoſe Articles. For as an adjudication of his Sacred Majeſty of their Title to any one of the ſaid Articles, had entitled them to All: ſo an adjudication of his Majeſty in Council, That they had not a right to that One they pleaded for, has adjudg'd them to have no right to any.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38538:23"/>
               <p>2. Was not his late Majeſty of glorious memory before thoſe Articles; (1) preingaged to the Adventurers for many of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Lands in <hi>Ireland;</hi> (2) in the ſtricteſt form of Ingagement, even by an Ingagement in Parliament; (3.) on the account of ſtricteſt Juſtice, even by way of ſale; (4) on the beſt account o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſale, the end thereof being to reduce the Iriſh Rebels: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might not theſe Arguments which P. W. urgeth in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt the breach of publick Faith, be at leaſt more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyable to this Engagement of his late Majeſty, to his now Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Declaration at <hi>Breda,</hi> and his Gracious Declaration of the 30. of <hi>November</hi> 1660. which were all Acts of Choyce, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation and Freedom: than to thoſe Articles of 1648. which was an Act of Neceſſity and Rebellious force. The Caſuiſts and Schoolmen will eaſily reſolve P. W. that the later and leſſer Obligation, ought to give place to the elder and greater. But if P. W. object, That if his Majeſty were under an Obligation preceding and oppoſite to theirs, why did he enter into an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation unto them? To that I anſwer, 1. That then it was not <hi>Res integr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> for his Majeſties Rebellious Subjects, even ſome of the Adventurers themſelves had ſuper-induc'd a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon his Majeſty, which as he could not foreſee when he made his firſt Contract: ſo by all the tyes of natural preſervation, he was bound to take away, when they were brought upon him; and it could not be a breach of Faith in the King to them, who made it (as things then ſtood) impoſſible to perform it. 2. Though Neceſſity be an unhappy plea, yet when 'tis a true, it is an allowable one. 3. That very Neceſsity which conſtrain'd his Majeſty to thoſe Articles, had they been obſerved by thoſe with whom they were made, would have invited all honeſt Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen to have cheerfully waited, till by the expected fruits and effects of that Peace, his Majeſty might have been enabled to have ſatisfied them; nay they would rather have loſt their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, than his Majeſty ſhould have broken his Faith with them, that had kept it with him, and would have been ſo ſerviceable to him; beſides his Majeſty might have been ſo ſoon reſeated in his Throne, that the debts of the Crown would have been ſo ſmall, and his Subjects ability and affections ſo great, that he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38538:24"/> might and would eaſily have ſatisfied the Adventurers deſires, without forfeited Land in Ireland, even by their own conſent. But the breach on the Iriſh Papiſts ſide, has occaſion'd ſo long and chargeable a War, that their forfeitures, together with the vaſt ſums ſent out of England into Ireland, and raiſed in Ireland it ſelf, are ſcarce able to defray that expence, which their own violation of Faith has engaged the Crown in: ſo that it is but juſt, that the Bear-skin (as far as it will go) ſhould contribute to pay for the healing of thoſe Wounds, which the Bear it ſelf had given. His Sacred Majeſty in the 3. page of his Declaration, ſpeaking upon theſe Articles, uſes theſe very words, <hi>viz. When they who wickedly uſurped the Authority in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, had erected that odious Court, for the taking away the life of Our dear Father; no body can wonder that we were deſirous, though upon DIFFIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LT CONDITIONS, to get ſuch an united power of Our own Subjects, as might have been able; with Gods bleſſing, to have prevented that infamous and horrible Parricide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe clear and Royal expreſsions the World may ſee what was the only incentive to his Majeſty, for his granting of that Peace, even no leſs than the <hi>preventing of the Murther of his bleſſed Father,</hi> and the bloody conſequences of it: And therefore if That were the hopefull effect of thoſe Conceſsions, had they been obſerved on the Iriſh ſide; may not we (without too much ſtraining) inferr, that the breach on their ſide, contributed to, if not acted that unparallel'd Crime. To commit the Sin, and not to prevent the Sin, when men have the preventative power of it, are very near ally'd, if not the ſame Crimes.</p>
               <p>I ſhall alſo here again obſerve, that what P. W. calls <hi>Freely putting themſelves and their power into my L. Lievtenants hands;</hi> his Sacred Majeſty juſtly marks with theſe obſervable expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, [<hi>upon difficult Conditions;</hi>] may I not therefore from thence alſo well infer, That P. W's. Clients do nothing ſo freely as when they put difficult Conditions on his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Though I have ſaid and prov'd by undeniable evidences, That the Iriſh Papiſts have violated and broken the Articles they extorted in 1648. yet becauſs <hi>P. W</hi>'s. Tenents obliges <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38538:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
